A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Behavioral Sciences Division, Office Files of Bernard Berelson FA1508
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Behavioral Sciences Division, Office Files of Bernard Berelson
1951-1966
Rockefeller Archive Center
Berelson, Bernard (1912-1979)
Ford Foundation
FA1508
1 Cubic Feet 3 boxes (2 letter document containers and 1 half-letter document containers)
Biographical / Historical
Bernard Berelson (1912-1979) was a social scientist and foundation executive who specialized in many fields, including library science, population studies, mass communication, and education. Berelson earned a bachelor's degree from Whitman College in 1934, and he went on to study library science at the University of Washington. In 1941, Berelson earned his doctorate at the University of Chicago. During World War II, he worked in Washington as an analyst of German opinion at the Office of War Information (OWI). After the War, Berelson was the research director of the Bureau of Applied Social Research at Columbia University from 1944 to 1946. He left this position for the University of Chicago, where he was a professor of library science and social sciences, and later, dean of the Graduate Library School and chairman of the Committee on Communication.
In 1951, Berelson joined the staff of the Ford Foundation in Pasadena, California, to lead what would become the Behavioral Sciences Division. Two overarching goals of the program were "to increase scientific knowledge of human behavior, and to facilitate the application of such knowledge to human affairs." Berelson was involved in projects that analyzed the study and scholarship of behavioral science, a term he is credited with popularizing. He studied the number of graduate degrees awarded to students in anthropology, sociology, psychology, and political science. He also analyzed recent publications in these fields. The Behavioral Sciences Division allocated fellowship funding for behavioral scientists, established the Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences at Stanford University, surveyed graduate programs in behavioral science, and granted $1,725,000 to 30 university presses over a period of five years to increase book publication in the humanities and social sciences. In 1957, Berelson left the Foundation to return to the University of Chicago to become a professor of behavioral sciences and director of the Study of Graduate Education. The Behavioral Sciences Division terminated in 1957. During its six-year existence, the Division distributed 218 grants totaling nearly $24 million to eighty-five institutions in the United States and abroad.
In 1962, Berelson joined the Population Council and served as its president from 1968-1974. Upon his retirement, he remained an active senior fellow with the Council until his death in 1979.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the office files of Bernard Berelson who served as Director of the Behavioral Sciences Division at the Ford Foundation from 1951-1957 as well as materials related to programs that extended beyond Berelson's time at the Foundation. Materials within the collection include correspondence, reports, notes, and data tables that analyze the behavioral sciences as an academic discipline. There are also grant proposals, fellowship information, and notes and correspondence regarding the university presses program, a program that allocated $1,725,000 to 30 university presses over a period of five years to increase book publication in the humanities and social sciences.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into one series: Behavioral Sciences Office Files.
The material is arranged as it was received from the Ford Foundation.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary. This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 by the Ford Foundation and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2019:014.
Anthropology; Behavioral sciences; Education (Graduate); Political science; Psychology; Sociology; University presses
- Behavioral Sciences Office Files, 1951-1966; 1
  - Behavioral Sciences - Administrative Processes - Bibliography - Papers of Bernard Berelson, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Correspondence, surveys of contributions in the fields of anthropology, political science, psychology, and sociology, surveys of doctorates issued by universities, guide to card file on behavioral science contributors/contributions, Memorial Policy in Social Science (Extracts from various memoranda and dockets), notecards related to subjects taught at various universities
  - Behavioral Sciences - Basic Research (Background Information), 1962-1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    General description, Report - Grants for Behavioral Sciences, 1952-1962, handwritten notes related to grants in behavioral sciences, list of graduate fellowships 1953-1954
    Cross reference grants lists - Research in the Behavioral Sciences:
    PA57-380 - University of Washington
    PA57-381, PA59-442, PA60-466 - Chicago University
    PA57-380 - Columbia University
    PA57-383 - University of Geneva
    PA57-384 - Harvard University
    PA57-385 - University of California (Berkeley)
    PA57-386 - Yale University
    PA57-387 - University of Minnesota
    PA57-388 - Institute of Living
    PA57-389 - Stanford University
    PA57-390 - Swarthmore College
    PA57-392 - University of Michigan
    PA57-371 - Columbia University
    PA57-372 - University of Michigan
    PA57-377 - Harvard University
    PA57-391 - University of California (Berkeley)
    PA57-393 - Cornell University
    PA57-394 - Chicago University
    PA57-415 - Yale University
    Cross Reference - Research in Individual Behavior and Human Relations:
    PA50-5 - University of California (Berkeley)
    PA50-123 - University of Chicago
    PA50-132 - Columbia University
    PA50-239 - Cornell University
    PA50-248 - Harvard College
    PA50-251 - University of Illinois
    PA50-255 - University of Michigan
    PA50-259 - University of Minnesota
    PA50-266 - University of North Carolina
    PA50-268 - University of Pennsylvania
    PA50-269 - Princeton University
    PA50-275 - Social Science Research Council
    PA50-284 - Yale University
  - Behavioral Sciences - As Applied to the Humanities - Correspondence with/Reports Written by W. McNeil Lowry, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Correspondence, summary of meeting with Dr. Robert Merton, Economic and Social Positions of the Artist and His Institutions - Phase I: Descriptive and Statistical and Phase II: Analytical and Evaluative, Report of Exploratory Session with Dean Manheimer over Outline for Phase I of Study, Report by McNeil Lowry - The Visual Arts, Music, Creative Writing Other Than Dramatic, The Theatre, The Visual Arts, Music, The Theatre
  - Behavioral Sciences - Reports and Notes, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes:
    Editorial - The Ford Foundation and the Behavioral Sciences - Reprinted from Human Organization, Volume 19, No. 2, Summer 1960
    Query: What should The Ford Foundation do about the behavioral sciences? A. Terminate Support, B. Continue Support
    Five Year Report on Program V
    Grants to Institutions
    The Present Situation
  - Behavioral Sciences - Development of Program Area V (2 folders), 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Behavioral Sciences - Graduate Education - Correspondence, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Behavioral Sciences - Graduate Education - Reports and Drafts, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Behavioral Sciences - Graduate Education - Interoffice Memos, Interviews, and Inter-foundation Reports, 1955-1966 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Behavioral Sciences - Graduate Education - Drafts, Notes, Graphs, Miscellaneous Brochures, and Clippings, circa 1955-1960 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Behavioral Sciences - Graduate Education - William McPeak Memo and Correspondence, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Behavioral Sciences - Graduate Education - "Committee of Fifteen" (The Fund for the Advancement of Education), 1954-1956 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Notes, comments, and reports on graduate education
    Includes the final publication - The Graduate School Today and Tomorrow: Reflections for the Profession's Consideration, Committee of Fifteen, Jacques Barzun, Harvie Branscomb, Paul Buck, Philip Davidson, William DeVane, John Dodds, Clarence Faust, Frederick Hard, Charles Johnson, Roger McCutcheon, Donald Morrison, Whitney Oates, Philip Rice, F. W. Strothmann, C. Vann Woodward, December 1955
  - Behavioral Sciences - Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences, 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Study committee notes and correspondence
  - Behavioral Sciences - Ford Faculty Apprenticeship Program Proposal and A Proposal for the Study of the Behavioral Sciences, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Behavioral Sciences - Foundation Fellowships, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Behavioral Sciences - Program Director Job Description, 1956 April 26 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Behavioral Sciences - University Presses Program - Notes and Correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Correspondence with Edward D'Arms
  - Behavioral Sciences - University Presses Program - W. McNeil Lowry's Correspondence with University Presses, 1956-1960 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Behavioral Sciences - University Presses Program - Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Behavioral Sciences - American University Publishing, 1955: A Supplement to the "Report on American University Presses" by Chester Kerr, The Association of American University Presses, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Behavioral Sciences - University Presses Program - Evaluation and Review, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)